Finding Aid for William A. Hiltner papers, 1942-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William A. Hiltner papers 1942-1991
Hiltner, W. A. (William Albert), 1914-
921097 Aa 2
Astronomer, professor of astronomy at the University of Chicago, later at the University of Michigan. Biographical material, correspondence, topical files, teaching materials, research files, and photographs relating to professional interests, including his interest in photoelectric photometry leading to the discovery of interstellar polarization; also files relating to various observatories.
11 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Mrs. Ruth Hiltner (donor no. 7990 ) in beginning in 1991.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William A. Hiltner was born in North Creek, Ohio on August 27, 1914. He received a B.S. in math and physics from the University of Toledo in 1937. Subsequently, he earned a M.S. degree in 1938 and a Ph.D. in astronomy in 1942 from the University of Michigan. In 1967 he was awarded an honorary degree from the University of Toledo. From 1942 through 1970, Hiltner was on the faculty at the University of Chicago and during parts of his tenure there was the director of Yerkes Observatory (1963-1966) and acting director of Cerro Tololo InterAmerican Observatory (1966-1967) in Chile. Hiltner's tenure at the University of Michigan began in 1970 when he was appointed chairman of the Department of Astronomy and director of University Observatories. He was chairman of the department until 1983 and retired from the University of Michigan in 1985.
The focus of Hiltner's research was work on photoelectric photometry which led to the discovery of interstellar polarization. Additionally, his work enabled the identification of a number of X-ray sources and provided the first evidence for a magnetic field pervading the Milky Way galaxy. To help with his ground breaking research, Hiltner designed and developed new instrumental techniques and applications. During his tenure at the University of Michigan, Hiltner was responsible for the establishment of the McGraw-Hill Observatory on Kitt Peak in Arizona which involved the moving of a 1.3-meter reflector from Dexter, Michigan to Arizona and the construction and implementation of a 2.4-meter telescope, which has now been named in his honor. During his lifetime, Hiltner produced more than 200 research papers, book chapters, and other scientific contributions (a partial bibliography may be found in the topical files under "Letters of Merit").
Hiltner was a member of the International Astronomical Union; the American Astronomical Society; the Astronomical Society of the Pacific; and, the Optical Society of America. He was also a founder and extremely active member of the Associated Universities for Research in Astronomy (AURA) which runs the National Optical Astronomy Observatories in Arizona and Chile.
William A. Hiltner died September 30, 1991.
The papers of William A. Hiltner cover his active role both in the Department of Astronomy at the University of Michigan and in the field of astronomy in general. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence and topical files. Also included are some teaching and research materials and files relating to his professional associations.
Subjects:
Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy.; Astronomical observatories.; Astronomy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Cerro Tololo Inter-American Observatory.; Hiltner, W. A. (William Albert), 1914-; Kitt Peak National Observatory.; University of Chicago.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Yerkes Observatory.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Astronomical observatories.; Astronomy.; Celestial bodies.; Cerro Tololo Inter-American Observatory.; Kitt Peak National Observatory.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence 1942-1991
  The Correspondence series dates from 1942 to 1991. Up until approximately 1967, the files were arranged alphabetically within chronological blocks of time. Beginning in 1967, the files were arranged in chronological order only. The letters concerns Hiltner's professional activities, his research and the research of colleagues.
  - 1942-1955
    - A-I (miscellaneous), 10 folders (Box 6)
    - Aller, Lawrence 1943-1955 (Box 6)
    - Baade, Walker 1948-1949 (Box 6)
    - Bartky, Walter 1946-1953 (Box 6)
    - Benes, John 1952-1955 (Box 6)
    - Binnendjik, L. 1951-1953 (Box 6)
    - Bowen, I.S. 1946-1952 (Box 6)
    - Buchele, William 1943-1946 (Box 6)
    - Burns, Jay 1953-1955 (Box 6)
    - Chandrasekhar, S. 1946-1955 (Box 6)
    - Code, Arthur D. 1948-1951 (Box 6)
    - Dershem, Elmer 1943-1947 (Box 6)
    - Dieke, G.H. 1947-1948 (Box 6)
    - Edmonds, Frank 1950-1951 (Box 6)
    - Edmondson, Frank K. 1945-1952 (Box 6)
    - Esterline-Angus Company 1946-1947 (Box 6)
    - Fowler, Richard G. 1946-1954 (Box 6)
    - Greenstein, Jesse 1942-1954 (Box 6)
    - Hall, John 1948-1955 (Box 6)
    - Haro, Guillermo 1953-1955 (Box 6)
    - Herzberg, Garo 1946-1952 (Box 6)
    - Hinds, Dorothy 1946-1951 (Box 6)
    - Hodges, Paul 1947-1954 (Box 6)
    - Horak, Henry 1951-1954 (Box 6)
    - Irwin, John 1947-1954 (Box 6)
    - J-S (Miscellaneous), 15 folders (Box 7)
    - Johnson, Harold 1949-1955, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Jose, Paul D. 1947-1950 (Box 7)
    - Kodak-Eastman Company 1942-1955 (Box 7)
    - Krebs, Marlyn 1950-1955 (Box 7)
    - Krogman, W.L. 1946-1953 (Box 7)
    - Kron, Gerry 1946-1953 (Box 7)
    - Kuiper, Gerald 1943-1955, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Morgan, William W. 1945-1954 (Box 7)
    - Ohman, Yngue 1949-1950 (Box 7)
    - Oort, J.H. 1947-1949 (Box 7)
    - Page, Thornton 1949-1951 (Box 7)
    - Polaroid Company 1949-1955 (Box 7)
    - Russell, Henry Norris 1943-1947 (Box 7)
    - Stromgren, Bengt 1948-1955 (Box 7)
    - S-Z (Miscellaneous), 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Struve, Otto 1942-1955, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Swings, Pol 1942-1953 (Box 8)
    - Whitford, A.E. 1948-1953 (Box 8)
    - Williams, Robley 1941-1947 (Box 8)
  - 1955-1962
    - A-I (Miscellaneous), 10 folders (Box 8)
    - Bahner, Klaus 1958-1961 (Box 8)
    - Baum, William 1955-1961 (Box 8)
    - Behr, Alfred 1958-1961 (Box 8)
    - Blaauw, Adriaan and Borgman January 1958-1959 (Box 8)
    - Burbidge, Margaret and Geoffrey 1959-1961 (Box 8)
    - Burns, Jay 1956-1961, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Carrasco, Lily 1956-1958 (Box 8)
    - Chamberlain, Joe 1958-1960 (Box 8)
    - Haro, Guillermo 1955-1961, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - J-W (Miscellaneous), 16 folders (Box 9)
    - Johnson, Harold 1955-1961, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Keller, Geoffrey 1955-1961 (Box 9)
    - Kron, Gerald 1957-1958 (Box 9)
    - Lallemand, A. 1955-1960 (Box 9)
    - Miller, Richard H. 1955-1960 (Box 9)
    - Miczaika, G.R. 1955-1959 (Box 9)
  - 1962-1964
    - A-I (Miscellaneous), 9 folders (Box 9)
    - Burns, Jay (Box 9)
    - Chivens, Clyde (Box 9)
    - J-Z, 16 folders (Box 10)
  - 1965-1967
    - A-S (Miscellaneous), 19 folders (Box 10)
    - Ford, W. Kent Jr. (Box 10)
    - T-Z (Miscellaneous), 4 folders (Box 11)
    - Wares, Gordon W. (Box 11)
    - Wilcock, W.L. (Box 11)
    - Williams, Marjorie (Box 11)
  - 1967-1980, 25 folders (Box 11)
    (include a few earlier dated letters)
  - 1981-1991, 11 folders (Box 1)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series represent files established by Hiltner concerning individuals, places and events. The researcher should consult both these files and the correspondence series for material on any given topic.
  - Albers, Harry R. (Box 1)
  - American Astronomical Society Meeting 1961 (Box 1)
  - Astrophysical Journal (Box 1)
  - Astro-Science Workshop (Box 1)
  - BASF Wyandotte Talk 10/21/1981 (Box 1)
  - Baustian, William W. (Box 1)
  - Behr, Alfred (Box 1)
  - Boley, Forrest I. (Box 1)
  - Bradt, Hale (Box 1)
  - Burbidge, Geoffrey and Margaret (Box 1)
  - Case Western Reserve University, Schmidt Telescope (Box 1)
  - Chivens, Clyde (Box 1)
  - Commemorative Letters (Box 1)
  - Copernicus Committee (Box 1)
  - Cowley, Anne and Charles (Box 1)
  - Curtis Memorial Telescope--Quartz Corrector (Box 1)
  - Detroit Observatory Restoration (Box 1)
  - Garrison, Robert (Box 1)
  - Genet, Russell M. (Box 1)
  - Girl Scouts (Box 1)
  - Great Lakes Astronomy Symposium, Fifth Annual (Box 1)
  - Hiltner, Ruth (Box 1)
  - Hiltner Fund in Astronomy, correspondence (Box 1)
  - International Amateur-Professional Photoelectric Photometry Communication (Box 1)
  - International Astronomical Union
    - 9th General Assembly, Dublin, Ireland 1955, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 10th General Assembly, Moscow, Russia 1958 (Box 1)
    - Commission Meetings, Prague, Czechoslovakia 1967 (Box 1)
  - Jones & Carr (KPNO Facilities Engineering Dept.) (Box 1)
  - Kraft, Robert P. (Box 1)
  - Kunkel, William (Box 1)
  - Lawrence Radiation Laboratory (Box 1)
  - Lecture Announcements 1952-1955 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Merit (Box 1)
  - Ludden, Dwight (Box 1)
  - Mayall, Nick (Box 1)
  - McClintock, Jeff (Box 1)
  - McMath-Hulbert Observatory (Box 1)
  - Mexico Trip 1961 (Box 2)
  - Midwest Radio Astronomy (Box 2)
  - Miller, R.H. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (letters/writings/notes) (Box 2)
  - Mohler, Orren C. (Box 2)
  - Montgomery, Earl F. (Box 2)
  - Mook, D.E., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - National Aeronautics and Space Administration
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Grant Materials NGR 14-001-054 (Box 2)
  - National Research Council 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - "Nature in Action" (Television program) 1951 (Box 2)
  - Odell, Robert (Box 2)
  - Office of Naval Research (ONR) 1947-1951 (Box 2)
  - Osawa, Kiyotern (Box 2)
  - Osmer, Patrick S. (Box 2)
  - Overberger, Charles G. (Box 2)
  - Pel, John (Box 2)
  - Pishmish, Parish (Box 2)
  - Prince, Gregory S. (Box 2)
  - Sanduleak, Nick (Box 2)
  - Schild, Rudolph (Box 2)
  - Smith, Harlin (Box 2)
  - Spradlin, Paul (Box 2)
  - Tonantzilla Observatory, Mexico 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Ultra-Violet, Optical, and Infra-Red (UVOIR) Space Astronomy (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Department of Astronomy; Overview of Chairmanship circa 1981 (Box 2)
  - Wartik, Thomas (Box 2)
  - Williams, Glen (Box 2)
- Association of Universities for Research in Astronomy (AURA)
  The Associated Universities for Research in Astronomy (AURA) series includes some of the records generated by a search committee. While Hiltner was an active member of AURA, during 1976 and 1977 he also served as chairman of the search committee that was charged with finding a new director for the organization. The records in this series relate to the formation of the search committee, the nomination of candidates, the consideration of candidates, and the selection of a new director.
  - Applications for Directorship (Box 2)
  - Cerro Morado (Box 2)
  - Cerro Tololo 1967
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Edmondson, Frank (Box 2)
    - General Information (Box 2)
    - Mayall, Nick (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Reports on Construction (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory
    - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - General Information (Box 2)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory/Cerro Tololo Inter-America Observatory (KPNO/CTIO) Visiting Committee Reports (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous notes/correspondence (Box 3)
  - Search Committee Candidates (Box 3)
  - Search Committee Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Search Committee Selection (Box 3)
- University of Chicago Materials 1944-1969
  The University of Chicago series consist of a number of reports and research projects which Hiltner generated during his tenure at the University of Chicago. Included are research proposals made to the National Foundation of Science, annual reports of Yerkes Observatory and progress reports of a project for the United States Air Force titled "Development of an Electrographic Image Tube." This series, while incomplete, does show a sampling of Hiltner's interests and activities during his twenty-seven years at the University of Chicago.
  - Correspondence 1965-1969 (Box 3)
  - Department of Astronomy
    - Minutes, grant proposals, etc. 1956-1959 (Box 3)
    - Council minutes, constitution, etc. 1949-1959 (Box 3)
  - Development of an Electrographic Image Tube 1958-1963, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Faculty Memoranda 1961-1968 (Box 3)
  - History of Photoelectric Phenomenon undated (Box 3)
  - National Science Foundation Proposals 1961-1969, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Public Relations 1947-1949 (Box 3)
  - Reports and Recommendations (Box 3)
  - Use of Thin Foil Image Converters for More Rapid
    - Photography 1957-1959 (Box 3)
  - Yerkes Observatory
    - Annual Reports 1944-1962 (Box 3)
    - 24" Telescope Transfer (Box 3)
- Teaching Materials and evaluations
  Teaching Materials and Evaluations consists of syllabi and exams for various astronomy courses taught or supervised by Hiltner. A few lecture notes and annotated comments on handouts reflect Hiltner's active role in the teaching process. Furthermore, the exams and syllabi themselves indicate the astronomical issues and topics deemed important for basic knowledge and understanding of the field during this time period. Additionally, student evaluations from varying time periods indicate the overall popularity of Hiltner's courses.
  - Astronomy 101/111 exams (Box 3)
  - Astronomy 102/112 exams
    - 1972-1977 (Box 3)
    - 1978-1981, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Astronomy 130 exams 1980 (Box 3)
  - Astronomy 221 exams 1979/80 (Box 3)
  - Astronomy 222 exams 1980/81 (Box 3)
  - Astronomy 230 syllabus 1975 (Box 3)
  - Astronomy 321 exam 1980 (Box 3)
  - Astronomy 409 exams 1979 (Box 3)
  - College 152-2 exams 1980 (Box 3)
  - Course Evaluations
    - 1971 (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Teaching Materials (Box 3)
- Michigan, Dartmouth, MIT (MDM) Astronomy Consortium 1972-1982
  Michigan, Dartmouth, MIT (MDM) Astronomy Consortium series consists of correspondence and technical papers representing agreements between astronomers at The University of Michigan, MIT and Dartmouth University to construct a new observatory at Kitt Peak, Arizona. The series documents many aspects of relocating Michigan's 1.3-meter telescope to the new McGraw-Hill Observatory, including design specifications and various funding requests. Correspondence and newspaper articles provide important background information for the project and photographs document the physical packing and moving of the reflector. Also included in the series are the papers documenting Hiltner's proposal to build a 2.4-meter telescope at Kitt Peak. This series shows the active role that Hiltner took in cooperating with other astronomers to build and maintain adequate sites and increasingly sophisticated equipment for research observations.
  - MDM Consortium Agreements 1974 (Box 4)
  - Relocation of 1.3-meter telescope to Kitt Peak
    - Correspondence 1972-1974 (Box 4)
    - Funding Proposals 1974 (Box 4)
    - Mechanical Specifications
      - General (Box 4)
      - Dome (Box 4)
      - Mirror Support (Box 4)
    - News Releases/Articles 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - Photographs 1974-1975 (Box 4)
  - McGraw-Hill Observatory
    - Observing Schedules/Requests 1972-1980 (Box 4)
    - Photographs, 1974-1975 (Box 4)
    - User Information 1975 (Box 4)
  - 2.4-meter Hiltner Telescope
    - Correspondence 1979-1982 (Box 4)
    - Design Specifications, Blueprints 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    - Funding Proposals 1982 (Box 4)
    - Mechanical Specifications
      - All-Refracting UV Grism Spectrometer (Box 4)
      - Encoders (Box 4)
      - Mirror (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Notes (Box 4)
    - News Releases/Articles (Box 4)
- Research Materials
  Research Materials represent a miscellaneous conglomeration of photographs and data sheets. One of the limitations of this series is its incomplete nature. The series is arranged by those astronomical bodies such as stars and nebula that could be identified from the materials. The remaining photographs and data sheets may be found under general headings. Of special interest are the data and correspondence Hiltner generated during his involvement in the global observations of Sco-X-1 during the late 1960s. This series shows the wide range of Hiltner's research interests. Clarification of some items in the research materials series may be found in the chronological correspondence and topical files series.
  - Data Runs (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous Observations (Box 4)
  - Optical Observations of HD 77481 and a Model for the System HD 77581-2U 0 990-40 (Box 5)
  - Observation Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Sco X-1 1969-1973 (Box 5)
  - 3U 1636-53 (Box 5)
  - 3U 1727-33 (Box 5)
  - AM HERC-suspected X-ray source (Box 5)
  - CD-33 12119 (Box 5)
  - Cen X-3 (Box 5)
  - CT 10 (4 meter) (Box 5)
  - Cyg X-2 (7/17/72) (Box 5)
  - Cyg XR-2 (Box 5)
  - LMC X-2 (Box 5)
  - NN Centauri (Box 5)
  - Sco X-1 (Box 5)
  - WRA 977 (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - 1624-49 (Box 5)
    - 3U0614+09 (Box 5)
    - 3U1705-44 (Box 5)
    - 4m Blowups (Box 5)
    - GX 17+2/GX 9+1 (Box 5)
    - HD 152248+152218 (Box 5)
    - NGC 6231 (Box 5)
    - PH-3705-5 (Box 5)
    - X-ray (Box 5)
    - Vela X (Box 5)
    - Unidentified research observations (Box 5)
  - Research Notebooks, 5 folders (Box 5)
- Biographical and Personal Material
  Biographical and Personal Materials is a small series containing a short biographical sketch of Hiltner and a bibliography of his published works. "Political Correspondence" gives a slight idea of Hiltner's political beliefs on the Vietnam War and civil liberties through limited correspondence with politicians.
  - Biographies and Bibliographies (Box 5)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 5)
  - Political Correspondence (Box 5)
- Writings
  Writings is a small series with Hiltner's dissertation being the most significant holding. "Articles and Reports" contains a small and random collection of journal articles, conference papers, and grant reports from the mid-1950s.
  - Articles and Reports 1953-1957 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscript Pages (Box 5)
  - A Spectrophotometric Study of B and Be Stars (Dissertation), 1942 (Box 5)
- Photographic Materials
  The Photographic Materials series contains primarily photographs of observatories during various phases of construction and operation. "Astronomical Charts" holds a small number of photographic mappings of stars and other celestial objects.
  - Astronomical Charts (Box 5)
  - Cerro Tololo Inter-America Observatory Construction (Box 5)
  - Construction Sites (Unknown) (Box 5)
  - Kitt Peak National Observatory Construction (Box 5)
  - Observatories (Box 5)
  - People (Box 5)
  - Telescopes (Box 5)